This week, we saw two families of public
encryption systems. One family was built
这次我们来学习一下两类公共加密系统，一个是基于陷门函数尤其
from trapdoor functions, and particularly
RSA, and the other family was built from
包含了rsa函数，另一个是基于
the Diffie-Hellman protocol. In this last
segment, I wanna show you that both
Diffie-Hellman协议。在上一段中我为你们展示一下基于
families in fact follow from a more
general principle. The unifying theme is
一个更平常规则的两类系统。统一的题目就是
what's called a one-way function. So what
is a one-way function? Well, we've already
被我们叫做单向函数。什么是单向函数呢？我们之前已经研究
seen this concept briefly before. But
basically, a function from, one set to
它的简要概念。但是事实上，一个从单值指向另一个单值的函数
another, say, from X to Y is said to be
one way, if, in fact, there's an efficient
也就是从X到Y如果有有效的算法
algorithm that allows us to evaluate the
function F. So anyone can evaluate the
可以让我们求得函数F值，那我们就把这个函数叫做单向的。所以说每一个人
function F at any point of their choice.
However, inverting the function F should
使用他们各自的选择求得f的值。然而转化函数f
be difficult. That's what makes the
function one way. So what do I mean by
必须是不同的。这就是怎么是函数是单向的。我的意思是什么？
that? Well, you can think of the function
F as a function again mapping the set X to
你可以把这个函数F当做一个再次把x集合映射到y
the set Y. But it so happens in many
points in X could actually be mapped into
集合的函数，但是有很多x集合中的值可能会被映射到一个
a single point in Y. Now when they say
that the function is difficult to invert,
y集合中单独的值。现在一些人说这个函数很难转化，也是就是说
what I mean is that when I give you some
point inside of Y and I ask you find me
当我提供给你们一些y集合中的值并且要求你们求出
pre-image of this point, you won't be able
to point to any of these as a pre-image.
这个值的原项你不能得到所有的原象。
In other words, no efficient algorithm can
find any point that is the inverse of the
换句话来说，没有一个有效的算法可以找到转化后的给定y中的值对应的
given point Y. Now the way we say that
more precisely is that we say that for all
原象。我们说的更精确一点就是对于所有的
efficient algorithm A, if I chose a random
X in the set, capital X, and now I'm gonna
有效算法A，如果我选择了一个x集合里的随机数X，主要X，我现在给一个
give f(x) to algorithm A. And then, what
I'm gonna ask algorithm A to do, is
f（x）到算法A中。之后我想要求算法A求出
basically produce a pre-image of the point
f(x). Well, what does it mean that A
f（x)的原象。确切意思是否是
produced a pre-image of the point f(x)? It
means that if I apply the function f to
A算法要求的f(x)的原象?它只是意味着如果我给予一个对于A的输出f函数
the output of A, what I should get back
is, well, f(x). Let's think through this
而这个函数是我必须找到原象的。再让我们考虑一下。
one more time. So I chose a random point x
in Capital X. You know I give algorithm A
所以我必须选择一个x集合中的随机数x，你们知道我给出了算法A的函数
f(x). So I'm gonna give algorithm A this
point here. And now A is gonna produce
f(x)，我也给出算法A的注意点，现在A会得到一些
some points. So let's pretend that A
produces this point over here. And now I
数值。所以让我们假设算法得出的数值覆盖了这些。现在我想知道
wanna say that if I apply the function F
to this point here, that A produced, the
如果我提供了对于这些A得出的数值的函数F
probability that I get the same point that
I started with is negligible. In other
我得到跟开始时相同数值的可能性是可以忽略不计的，从另一句话来说
words the probability that algorithm A
was able to produce one of these three points is, in
就是算法可以得出这三个数值的可能性在实际上
fact, negligible. All he can do is produce
some other point that maps into something
是不存在的。它能做的就是得到一些别的映射进f（x）
other than f(x), okay? So, again, all
this is trying to do is just capture the
中的数值。好吧，这里要做的就是捕获给你们的
fact that given f(x), it's hard to find
some pre-image of f(x). So here's some
f(x)函数。因为很难去找到f（x）值的原象。所以这有一些
easy examples of functions that are not
one-way. For example, the identity
简单的非单向函数的例子。举个例子来说，一致性函数
function f(x) is equal to x is trivially
not one way because given f(x), I can
简单地f（x)等于x函数就是一个普通的不是单向函数，因为给定一个f(x)
easily come up with an inverse of f(x),
namely x. Similarly the function that will
我可以很容易的想到一个命名为x的f（x）的变形。相似的将所有的数值都
maps everything to zero is also not one
way. So in our picture, let the function
映射成0的函数同样也不是一个单向函数。所以在我们的课程里，把将
maps everything to zero simply looks as
follows. It takes all its points and maps
所有映射成0的函数看做下面的函数。它选取所有数值并将它们
them all to a single point. Well this
function is not one way because if I give
全部映射成一个单独的值。这个函数不是一个单向函数因为
you this point in the image, it's trivial
to find the pre-image. Namely, just pick
如果我给你一个项，它非常容易就可以找到一个原项。选取任一x
any point in capital X, and there will be
a pre-image of zero. And so, f(x) equal
集合中的元素，就会有一个原项0。f（x）等于
to zero is also not a one-way function.
And by the way, I didn't want to do it
0也不是一个单向函数。顺口说一句，我不想在这里讨论这个。
here. But if I define one-way functions
more formally, then it turns out that
但是如果我更加正式地定义单向函数，这就会证明
proving that one-way functions exist,
we'll have also proven that P is not equal
单向函数确实存在，我们也会证明P不等于
to NP. So, since we can't today, prove
that P is not equal to NP, basically we
NP。当然，今天我们还不会去证明P是不等于np，也不去证明
can't prove that one-way functions exist.
And we just have to assume that they do.
单向函数存在，我们现在必须假设它们是正确的。
So let's look at our first example of a
1-way function. Or at least a presumed
所以让我们看我们第一个单向函数的例子。或者最起码是一个
1-way function. And so we're gonna build
it from a pseudo random generator. And
假设中的单向函数。我们将会利用伪随机数生成器来建立这个函数，假设
suppose I have a function F from x to y
there is a secure pseudo random generator.
我有一个从x映射到y的函数F,存在一个安全的伪随机数生成器。
So the output of f s much larger than
the input. Remember, a pseudo-random
所以f s的输出远远大于输入，要记住，一个伪随机数生成器
generator takes a small seed and expands
it into a much larger output. And for
只需要很少的输入之后它会扩大出一个很大的输出，
example you can, you know, the pseudo
random generator maybe is built using
你们知道的，对于这个例子，伪随机数生成器可能利用
deterministic counter mode out of AES.
Well, it's fairly easy to see that if, in
AES确定的计数器模式来构建的。这样就能很容易的研究学习了，
fact, F is a secure pseudo random
generator, then F is in fact a one-way
事实上F是一个安全的伪随机数生成器，并且F也是一个单向函数
function. So our first example of a
one-way function is directly built from a
所以我们第一个单向函数是直接由
pseudo random generator. This is actually
kind of a trivial proof, so let's prove
伪随机数发生器构建的。这是仅仅是一个很不充分的证据，所以让我们
the contra positive. So suppose I have an
efficient algorithm that inverts F, okay?
从反面来证明。现在假设我有一个有效的算法可以变形F行吗?
So I'm proving the contra positive.
Suppose F is not one way. Then A is an
所以我开始从反面论证。假设f不是一个单向函数，之后A就是一个
efficient algorithm than an inverse F. And
now I need to build an algorithm B that
f的逆向有效算法。现在我就需要构建一个算法B来打破
breaks the pseudorandom generator. Ok, so I'm proving again by contra-positive. Okay so how do I break the
随机数生成器。我再从正反面来证明一下。我怎么做才能打破
pseudo-random generator? Well, all we do
is the following. So algorithm B is given
这个伪随机数生成器呢？我们要就是就是我下面说的。算法B被给与
some y in the set Y. And what it's gonna
do is the following, it's gonna try and
一些y集合里的数值y，之后就按下面说的来做。它将会尝试并且运行
run algorithm a on the input y. And now,
well, if y is the output of the
算法在输入的y上。现在，如果y是伪随机数生成器的输出，
pseudorandom generator, then algorithm A
will output the seed, and namely
算法A就会输出一些数据，之后就会被命名为
[inaudible] an element in X with, you
know, non-negligible probability. So what
【不可找到】在x集合中，你知道没有一点点可能性。所以我们要做的
we'll do is we'll apply the pseudorandom
generator again to the output of algorithm
就是提供伪随机数生成器再一次输入算法A的输出。
A. As I said, if y was the output of a
generator, then [A of A ???] will have output
就像我说的，如果y是生成器的输出，之后算法A就会有输出
the seed cuz it inverted the pseudorandom
generator. So if we apply the pseudorandom
因为它转化了伪随机数生成器。所以如果我们提供了伪随机数生成器
generator again to the output of A, what
we should get back is basically the y that
再一次输入A的输出，我们将会得到开始时我们的
we started with. Okay, so if this
condition holds we're gonna say we're
y值。所以在这种情况发生的时候我们就可以说
gonna output zero. And if this condition
doesn't hold, we're gonna output one
我们得到了输出0.如果这样的情况没有发生，我们将会得到输出
otherwise. That's it, that's our
distinguisher against a pseudo-random
这就是我们讲的正反面的伪随机数
generator. So if our distinguisher is
given a y that is the output of the pseudo
生成器。所以如果我们辨义成分是伪随机数生成器的输出y
random generator, then with non-negligible
probability, our distinguisher B will
没有一点点可能，我们的函数B将会
output zero. However, if our distinguisher
B is given a truly random string. Well, a
输出0。然而，如果我们的编译成分B输入的是一个真正的随机字符串，
truly random string doesn't have any seed
that causes the generator to output that
真的随机字符串是没有可以导致生成器输出的任何数据
string. And therefore our distinguishable
output one with again, with also very high
因此我们的假设成分输出一的可能性是
probability. And again I hope that's
clear. Basically, if we look at the set of
很高的。我希望这是明确的，如果我们看所有
all possible outputs, namely the set Y,
very few of those outputs happened to
可能的输出序列，即序列y，这些输出中的很少一部分
be the output of the pseudorandom
generator. So if we are just given an
刚好是伪随机发生器的输出，所以如果我们仅仅给出
output y over hearsay, that's not the
output of the pseudorandom generator, then
一个输出y,这不是伪随机发生器的输出
we rerun algorithm A on it. It can't
possibly produce a seed that will output
之后我们在这个输出值上重复运行算法A.这样不可能生成一个
this point starr because there is no
such seed. And as a result, since most
将输出起始点的种子。因为没有很多的种子。因此
points actually are not in the image of
the pseudorandom generator, most points
实际上大多数点不在伪随机发生器的影像范围之内，
will not have a seed that, maps the
generator to them and there's also where
大多数点没有种子，将生成器划入它们，这里
we were given a random point in Y, a truly
uniform point in Y, our distinguishable B
就是在y中我们被给出的一个随机点，一个真正均衡的点
will output 1 with very high
probability. However, if we are given a
我们这个可分辨的b将以很大的可能性输出1.但是如果我们给出
pseudo random output of a generator, then
algorithm A will output the corresponding
一个发生器的伪随机的输出，这个算法A将输出相一致的种子
seed. When we apply the generator to that
seed, we'll get the initial output y and
当我们把这个生成器用于这个种子时，将得到最初的输出y
therefore we'll output zero with
non-negligible probability. Okay, so if A
因此我们将以不可忽略的可能性输出0，好的
was able to invert F, then B is able to
break the generator. And since the
所以说如果A能转置F，那么b久能破解这个发生器。那么既然
generator is secure, algorithm A can't
invert F. And in particular, no efficient
这个发生器是安全的，算法A就不能转置F。尤其是，
algorithm can invert F. And therefore, F
is a one-way function. Excellent, so this
没有有效的算法可以用来转置F。因此，F是单向函数。
is a long discussion of kind of a minor
point. But all I wanted to show you is
很好，这是一个有关一个小点的长讨论。但是我想告诉你们的是
that in fact, a pseudo-random generator
directly gives us a one-way function.
实际上，一个伪随机生成器直接就给了我们一个单向函数
Unfortunately, this one-way function has
no special properties. And what that means
不幸的是，这个单向函数没有特殊的属性。这个的意思是
is it's actually difficult to use it for
key exchange or for public key encryption.
实际很难把这个函数用于密钥交换或者公钥加密
In some sense, the best key exchange we
can do with this, as far as we know, is
在某种程度上，我们能处理的最好的密钥交换方法，就我所知
Merkle puzzles. So now let's look at
our second example. The second example is
是Merkle 拼图。所以我们看一下我们的第二个例子。它是说
what I'm gonna call the discrete log one
way function. So let's fix a group, a
我把这个离散日志称作单向函数。所以我们确定一个组
cyclic group of order N the group G and
let g be some generator of the group
一个循环组的序列n和组G，并且令g是大写字母G的一些生成器
capital G so again I remind you that all
that means is, if I look at all powers of
我想提醒的是这些意思是如果我看了g的所有指数
g, then I basically span the entire group
capital G. And now let's define the
之后我就可以揣测整个大写字母G的值。现在让我们定义一下
following function. The function goes from
ZN to G and it's defined basically as the
下列函数。这些函数从Zn到G，随着g的幂次方x的变化而定义的。
exponentiation to the power of X. Okay, so
this maps any element between zero and n-1
好的这个就把0到n-1之间的所有元素
to an element of the group capital G
simply by raising g, little g to the
以g倍的倍数增长映射到G中的元素。小g是恰当的增长速度
appropriate power. And it's kind of
obvious that if the discrete log problem
这个很明显的是如果G组中离散日志
in the group capital G is hard, then in
fact f is one way. In fact, the one
是接近的，那么f就是单向函数。实际上，
wayness of f is the discrete log
assumption. So if the discrete log is
f的一种方式是离散日志的一种假设。所以说如果离散日志
hard, f is one way. Now the interesting
thing about this one-way functions is it's
是接近的，那么f就是一个单向函数。现在关于单向函数的一个有趣的事是
got some interesting properties. In
particular, if I give you f(x) and f(y)
它具有一些有趣的属性。例如，如果我给出函数f（x）和f(y)
I claim that it's very easy to compute
f(x + y). Even though we have no idea
很容易算出函数f(x+y)。即使我们不知道
what x or y are. All we're given is just f(x) and f(y), nevertheless, we can
x，y是什么。所给我们的仅仅是函数f(x)和f(y)，因此，
compute f(x + y). Let me ask you, how
would you do that? Well, just by rules of
我们可以计算出f（x+y）.我问一下，你们是怎样做到的呢？根据指数规律
exponentiation, basically, f(x + y)
is simply f(x) times f(y). And again,
实际上f(x+y)就是f(x)乘f(y)。
this is all done inside the group G. If
you're not convinced, simply recall that f(x + y)
这些都是在组G中操作的。如果你们不相信，简单回顾一下
is g to the (x + y). Which is
simply g to the x times g to the y, which
f(x+y)是g的（x+y）的次方。这就是简单的g的x次方乘g的y次方
is exactly what we have here. And this
simple property, this simple fact that the
这刚好就是我们这里所说的。这个简单的属性，是
function has this additive property, if
you think about it, is exactly what
这个函数具有这种加法的属性。如果你考虑一下
enables key exchange and public key
encryption. So, this additional property
这实际可以用于密钥交换和公开密钥加密。所以，单向函数的
of the one-way function is what enabled
all of public key cryptography. So let's
这种加法属性就是启用所有公钥加密
look at our next example the RSA one way
function so here we're going to choose two
所以让我们看一下另一个例子-RSA单向函数。这里我们将选择
primes p and q we're going to set N to be p
times q then were going to choose e that's
两个素数p和q，我们设置N等于p乘q，之后选择e使得e与
relatively prime to phi(N). And then, we
define the functions, and simply as a
P模pi（N）互素.现在我们定义函数，
function from ZN star to ZN star,
simply as f(x) equals x to the e. Okay,
作为一个从Zn*到Zn*的函数，使f(x)等于x的e次方。
so raising x to the power of e. And again
we say that this function is one way,
即使x以e的指数形式增长。我们说这个函数在RSA假设下是单向函数
simply under the RSA assumption. Again,
the RSA assumption is the assumption that
再者，RSA假设是指这个函数就是单向函数的假设
this function is one way. And the
interesting thing about this function is
有关这个函数的一个有趣的问题是
that it has properties similar to the one
that we saw on the previous slide, namely
它与我们之前看的单向函数具有相似的属性。即
the given f(x) and f(y), now we can
compute f(x  y) as opposed to f(x + y)
给出f(x)和f(y)，就可以算出函数f(x*y)与f（x+y）相对立.
So we say that this function has
a multiplicative property as opposed to
所以我们说这个函数乘法倍增的属性，与
the additive property on the previous
slide. But more importantly this is kind of
前面的加法属性相对立。但是这不是
not the most interesting thing about this
function. The really exciting thing about
有关函数最有趣的。最有趣的是
this function is it in fact has a
trapdoor. In other words there's a secret
这个函数有一个后门。换句话说存在
key that all of a sudden allows us to
invert this function. Even though without
一个秘密的密钥可以使我们转置这个函数。即使没有
the secret key the function is one way. As
far as we know. And this property, I'll
这个密钥这个函数还是单向函数。就我所知，这种属性
say, the fact that it has a trap door,
again, enabled all of public key
实际就有一个后门启用所有的公钥加密。
cryptography. I'll say that this trap door
also makes the RSA function especially
并且这个后门也使得RSA函数很适合用于数字签名。
well suited for digital signatures. In
week seven, we're gonna see that both the
在第7周，我们已经看了
RSA function and the discrete log
functions let us construct digital
RSA函数和离散日志函数使得我们构想出了数字签名
signatures. But the RSA function, because
it has a trap door, makes it very, very
但是RSA函数，由于它有后门，使得很容易从
easy to construct digital signatures from
it. And so, in fact, most digital
它构造出数字签名。实际上
signatures out there in the world, in
fact, rely on the RSA function just
现在的大多数数字签名依赖于RSA函数仅仅是
because it's so simple to build digital
signatures from it. So again, we see that
因为从它很容易构建出数字签名。接下来
this one-way function with the special
properties. It has a multiplicative
我们看一下这个单向函数的特殊属性。它具有倍数增长的属性
property and a trap door. Essentially
again, enables all of public key crypto. So
和一个后门。主要的是，启用公开密钥加密。
to summarize, the reason we are able to
build public key cryptography namely, the
现在总结一下，我们能构建公开密钥加密的原因，
reason we're able to do key exchange and
public key encryption and so on, is
和操作密钥交换的原因以及公钥加密的原因等等
because we're able to construct one-way
functions that have very, very special
是因为我们可以构造单向函数并且它具有非常非常特殊的性质
properties. In particular, they have these
properties that are sometimes called
特别地，它们的这些性质有时叫做
homomorphic properties, namely they're
given f(x) and f(y). We can construct
同态属性，即给出f(x),f(y），我们可以构造出
a f(x + y) or, f(x  y), and
some functions, like RSA, even have trap
f(x+y)或者f(x*y)或者其他一些函数，例如RSA
doors, which let us build digital
signatures very, very easily. But the main
甚至拥有一个后门，这后门使得我们很容易建立起数字签名。
thing I wanted to show you is that the
magic of public key crypto is basically made
但是我想告诉你们最核心的是这个公钥加密的神奇之处是
possible because of these one-way
functions with their special properties. So
实际由于这些单向函数所具有的特殊性质，
that's the end of this module and then
in week seven, we'll start with digital signatures.
好的，这就是这个模块的所有内容，在第7周，我们将开始学习数字签名